<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conscience eased: or, the main scruple which hath hitherto stuck most with conscionable men, against the taking of the Engagement removed. Where amongst other things is shewed, first, how farre the oath of allegiance, and the nationall League and Covenant are obligations; either in their legall intents unalterable or at this time no more binding and alterable. Secondly. How farre in a free people the subordinate officers of the state, have a right to judge of the proceedings of a king in that state. Thirdly, how Zedekia'es case in breaking his oath to the king of Babylon, and our case in making use of our freedome from the oath of allegiance, and supremacie to the king of England doe differ. / The author, John Dury.</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E625_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206464</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865621</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865621</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117867</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81909)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117867)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 96:E625[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Conscience eased: or, the main scruple which hath hitherto stuck most with conscionable men, against the taking of the Engagement removed. Where amongst other things is shewed, first, how farre the oath of allegiance, and the nationall League and Covenant are obligations; either in their legall intents unalterable or at this time no more binding and alterable. Secondly. How farre in a free people the subordinate officers of the state, have a right to judge of the proceedings of a king in that state. Thirdly, how Zedekia'es case in breaking his oath to the king of Babylon, and our case in making use of our freedome from the oath of allegiance, and supremacie to the king of England doe differ. / The author, John Dury.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37 [i.e. 38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.H. in Russell-street, neere the Piazza of the Covent-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 25-38 misnumbered.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb.25 1650", also the last two numbers of the imprint date have been marked through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Loyalty oaths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117867:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONSCIENCE EASED: <hi>OR,</hi> The main Scruple which hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſtuck moſt with conſcionable Men, againſt the taking of the Engagement removed.</p>
            <p>Where amongſt other things is ſhewed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, How farre the Oath of Allegiance, and the Nationall League and Covenant are Obligatins; either in their legall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts unalterable or at this time no more binding and alterable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly How farre in a free People the Subordinate Officers of the State, have a right to judge of the Proceedings of a King in that State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, How</hi> Zedekia'es <hi>caſe in breaking his Oath to the King of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and our caſe in making uſe of our freedome from the Oath of Allegiance, and Supremacie to the King of</hi> England <hi>doe differ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author, John Dury.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for T. H. in Ruſſell-ſtreet, neere the Piazza of the Covent-Garden, 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:117867:2"/>
            <head>The Errata.</head>
            <p>In page 1. line 10. for out ſoon after, read but ſoon after. p. 2. l. 22. for eaſe, r. caſe. p. 3. l. 1. for cauſe, r. clauſe in the note for ſummoned, r. ſummed. p. 5. l. 1. for muſt, r. moſt. l. 8 for many intentions, r. main intention is. p. 6. line 22. for ceaſe, r. croſſe, in l. 27 for oppreſſe, r. oppoſe. p. 7. l. 6. for of, r. to. line 9. for that, r. what. P. 10. l. 21. for out your ſelf, r. not your ſelf. p. 11. l. 4. for lawes r. lawleſſe. p. 12. l. 24. for Salvus, r. Salus p. 14. l. 14. for ſhew, r. Sphere. p. 16. l. 21. r. in our places. p. 17. l. 16. for revealed, r. reſolved. p. 20. l. 22. for have, read make. line the laſt, for Repreſentations, r. Repreſentatives. p. 25 l. 16. for accepted, r. I excepted. l. 23. r. they are not ſet. p. 28 l. 26. r. from under them. p. 33. l. 2. for inſtructed, r. intruſted. p. 36. l. 14. for him, r. us in the ſame line, for towards the K. of Babylon, r. towards our K with Zedekiahs condition, and his Oath binding him thereunto towards the K. of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, line 16. for maſter, r. matter. l. 17. for maſter r. matter. l. 35. for impoſed, r. implyed. p. 4. l. 19. for oblige, r. alledged.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117867:2"/>
            <head>CONSCIENCE EASED; <hi>OR,</hi> The main Scruple which hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſtuck moſt with conſcionable Men, againſt the taking of the Engagement, removed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Loving Friend, and Brother in Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had occaſion a few dayes agoe, to be with your Son in Law, which put me in mind of the diſcourſes, which you had with me when wee met laſt at his houſe: whereat I found my ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a guilt of ſome neglect of duty towards you, which now I am willing to confeſſe, to deprecate and amend. All that I have to ſay for my ſelf is, that ſoon after you were gone from hence; I did indeed, as I promiſed, put my thoughts concerning your Scruple to Paper; out ſoone after I went out of Town, &amp; al this laſt Summer, having bin variouſly diſtracted, and ſeveral times in the country, I could not atrend the ripening &amp; tranſcribing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117867:3"/> them to be imparted unto you: once I did ſet upon it to doe it, but was by a very preſſing occaſion taken off <note place="margin">The occaſion of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</note> againe, and ſome time ſince I have thought upon my promiſe, but I know not how I was willing to beleeve that happily you were ſatisfied, and ſhould not now need any ſuggeſtions which I could offer; and thus I have protracted the diſcharge of this Duty, till the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day I was ſtruck with ſome remorſe, and found cauſe to be aſhamed of my ſelfe, that all this while I had not made good my promiſe, made to you ſo long agoe; nor done that which was befitting my love and friendſhip to you in Chriſt; when as I did not certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know how farre your ſpirit was now quieted, which happily might lye as much under a doubt as ever: but that which doth now more effectually waken me to this performance, is that among all the objections againſt the Engagement; which I have bin obliged to reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſince I ſaw you; I doe not remember that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of your ſcruple, hath bin ſo deepely preſſed by any as by your ſelfe, and two or three dayes agoe, by a very honeſt and Godly Gentleman, who is pinched juſt as <note place="margin">and the ſcope there of which is to rrſolve the chiefe Scruple about the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> you were, and brought your eaſe fully againe to my mind; which I find when I lay it ſeriouſly to heart, the deepeſt, moſt inward, &amp; weightieſt Scruple of any that doth belong unto this buſineſſe: Therefore I ſhall now ar laſt (rather thus late, then never) acquaint you with what I have to ſay unto it to cleere it.</p>
            <p>I find by your Paper which I have, that your Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <note place="margin">which doth riſe from two cauſes, viz. 1. from the miſ-interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Engagement.</note> doth riſe from two things. Firſt, from your inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatiou of the words of the Engagement, when you put the whole Emphaſis in the latter clauſe thereof, <hi>viz. As it is now eſtabliſhed, without a King, und Houſe of Lords:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117867:3"/> which you conceive is the cauſe intended to be more directly obligatory then the fore-going; <hi>viz. To be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth of England.</hi> Secondly, becauſe you conceive that the ſence of the <note place="margin">2. From the contradiction betweene it, and the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> Engagement, as you underſtand it, doth containe a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect contradiction to the true meaning of the Oath of Allegiance, and of the Nationall Covenant; for your difficultie lyes in this, how to bring the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which you had in the former Engagements, to a Righteous Conſiſtencie, with the intention which you conceive you ought to have in this Engagement; all which difficultie you reduce to this practicall Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, under which your conſcience is concluded at preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">He that is under a lawfull Oath and Covenant of <note place="margin">both are ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned up in one practicall Sylogiſme.</note> the Lord, may not lawfully doe any ſuch thing as tendeth directly to take him off from acting in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous wayes, according to his Oath and Covenant: But I am (ſay you under a lawfull Oath and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord, to aſſiſt the juriſdictions annexed unto the Imperiall Crowne of this Realme, in the preſervation of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdome; and to endeavour to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament, as they were at the taking of the Covenant, and the entring into the preſent Engagement (as the proper ſence thereof is obvious to me) tendeth directly to take me off for ever from acting even in righteous wayes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Oath and Covenant: therefore I cannot lawfully enter thereinto, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 27.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To enlarge your ſpirit from this ſtreight, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive there is none other way but to cleere your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117867:4"/> from the miſtakes wherein you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <note place="margin">The way to reſolve the Scruple.</note> the intent of the Nationall Covenant, and of the Oath of Allegiance, compared with the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the preſent Engagement: for if it ſhal appeare that you run upon a cleere miſtake, concerning the true and righteous intents of any of theſe, then your Scruple will be found groundleſſe, becauſe the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition which you imagine to be betweene them (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which imagination your Conſcience is ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,) will be removed.</p>
            <p>To this effect then let me recommend unto your ſerious peruſall, that which I have ſaid to the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> &amp; <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Miniſters plea for non-ſubſcribers; where I ſhew their miſtake about the maine object of truth and faithfulneſſe required in the Engagement:; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their miſtak doth riſe from the miſconſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word Common-wealth, whereat you ſeeme not to be ſtaggered, ſo as they are, yet the grounds which are there obliged to cleere the ſence of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, may be of uſe to let you ſee that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis <note place="margin">The reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt part thereof.</note> cannot be there where you place it; but that the chief Emphaſis muſt be placed there, where the proper diſpoſition of the words, the nature of the matters expreſſed therein, and the publike Declarations given out to that very purpoſe, place it; for if their publike Declarations tend mainly to this, that to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs true &amp; faithful to the good of the Nation, they have conſtituted it to be a free State, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, by the removall of the King, and Houſe of Lords, who did uſurpe upon the Liberties of the Nation, and if the diſpoſition of the words and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Engagement, in their Grammaticall and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117867:4"/> Rationall Conſtruction, are muſt conſonant to this pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne intent of their Declatations; then we ought to place the Emphaſis of the words, not in the latter but in the former clauſe of the Engagement, becauſe the end wherefore the eſtabliſhment hath bin made without a King, and Houſe of Lords is, to make <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> a Common wealth, or free State; and therefore their many intentions to oblige every one, who ſhall live in it and enjoy the Liberties thereof, to be true and faithfull thereunto; and I am ſure you underſtand by Truth and Faithfulneſſe, not a meere negative, but a poſitive durifulneſſe: now to make the privative part of the eſtabliſhment to be the proper and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall object of ſuch a dutifulneſſe, when the poſitive eſtabliſhment is directly and immediately both in the poſition of the words, and in the property of the things ſet before it, ſeemes to me to proceed rather from a ſpirit of Jealouſie againſt their perſons, then from reaſon and ingenuity, in conſidering the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their words.</p>
            <p>If then nothing but an injurious Jealouſie doth put the Emphaſis where you place it, you may free your ſelfe from that ground of your Scruple, if you will be but ſo equitable, as to take the words of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in a ſence containing a juſt Duty which it cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beares; and if you can doe this, which I hope you will not find a Scruple to doe; then in the next place I ſhall intreate you to weigh theſe following Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Theſi</hi> without prejudice whether yea or no they are not ſound and without al exception; which if you doe, I hope they will conduce ſomewhat to the clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the reſt of your Scruple.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117867:5"/>1. That no humane Engagements, are, or ought to <note place="margin">Grounds to cleere the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the Scruple, ſhewing,</note> be binding to the conſcience of thoſe that take them; further, then the meaning of thoſe that give them is declared and aſſented unto by the taker.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no Engagements, whereof the meaning is <note n="1" place="margin">1. How farre humane En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement are binding.</note> declared, ought to be further binding to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then the intent declared is lawfull and allowable in the preſence of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the intents of no Engagements amongſt men can be further lawfull and allowable in the preſence of God, then as they are ſubordinate unto the main rules of our Chriſtian Profeſſion, and to the principles of naturall equity in humane ſocieties, whence this Corallary will follow.</p>
            <p>That if upon unfore-ſeen accidents and emergences <note n="2" place="margin">2. What may alter them.</note> (which alter the nature of all humane affaires) one and the ſame intent and deſigne, may be at one time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to theſe Rules and Principles, and at another time become diſagreable thereunto: then that intent and deſigne, not only may, but muſt be laid downe; for it is wholly unlawfull to maintain any purpoſes which ceaſe the practice or the profeſſion of duties flowing from theſe Rules and Principles.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the intents and deſigns of the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <note n="3" place="margin">3. What the intents of the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and National Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant are.</note> and of the National Covenant, were never made by the Parliaments, which framed them to contradict one another; or in their proper times to oppreſſe the rules of our Chriſtian profeſſion, or the principles of naturall equitie by which our ſociety is upheld: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in reſpect of certaine expreſſions, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the circumſtances of ſeverall times, wherein they were framed, they are cleerely different one from another.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:117867:5"/>
            <p>Whence this again will follow.</p>
            <p>That to be obliged to different intentions (though contrary) upon ſeverall occaſion (if both agree in their proper times to the forenamed Rules and Principles) this can be no breach of Dutie, or prejudice of Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That it doth belong onely to the Superiour <note n="4" place="margin">4. To whom it doth belong to Judge of publique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and deſignes and formes of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment.</note> powers of Humane ſocieties to judge and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine at all times that the publique Engagements and Deſignes ought to be, and what the forme of Government is, which is moſt proper for the times, and agreeable to Naturall Equitie to be yeelded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by all for common preſervation in Humane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Supreme Powers cannot be bound <note n="5" place="margin">5. What pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the ſupreme governours have in alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> up unalterably to any particular deſign or Humane Engagement; ſo as not to be free upon Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to entertain other deſignes and Engagements; when they ſhall think it moſt expedient for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſafety, and agreeable to Chriſtianity, nay, they are not onely free to doe this, but they are bound to it: elſe they are not faithfull to the Charge which God hath committed to them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That Subjects (that is, particular men in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <note n="6" place="margin">6. By what rule private men ſhould order their thoughts about the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Judge thereof.</note> ſtations) ought not to make themſelves inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of the intents of publique Engagements, otherwiſe then as they are agreeable to the Rules of Chriſtianity, and the Principles of Naturall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie; and ſo farre as they beare a ſenſe agreeable unto theſe; ſo farre they are bound in conſcience profeſſedly to own them, but if a ſenſe be impoſed upon them contrary to any of theſe, then they are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117867:6"/> not obliged to own that ſenſe.</p>
            <p>From whence I ſuppoſe this will follow.</p>
            <p>That whatſoever any mans private intention or <note n="7" place="margin">7. By what rule humane intents about publique en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements are altergble.</note> ſenſe of any publique Engagement may be, when he takes it: if afterward he findes cleerely and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly that either his intention was not ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate unto the publique at all, but onely to ſome private aime; or though it was truly in his thought ſubordinate thereunto, but not agreeable to the Rules and Principles of Chriſtianity and equitie; (I ſay) if he findes himſelf miſtaken either way; he is bound to rectifie his miſtake, and bring his ſenſe in obſerving the ſame unto the proportion of the forenamed Rules and Principles of Chriſtianity and naturall equitie.</p>
            <p>If theſe Propoſitions are to you, as to me they are, <note place="margin">The appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of theſe grounds to the ſcruple in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſhewing gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally that to come out of it wee muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider</note> ſound and without exception, I ſuppoſe they may ſhew you a way to come out of the ſtrait where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into your conſcience is concluded: for if you apply them to the caſe in hand; concerning this preſent engagement, with reſpect to former engagements; and do make all their intents, according to the circumſtances wherein they were begotten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurable one to another, by the rules and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtianity and naturall equitie; you will find either no cauſe at all to take up in your mind ſuch contradictory intentions, as you have imagined to bee therein: or if the circumſtances of affaires ſhall bee found ſuch, as will inforce by theſe rules and principles to allow of a change of intentions in the latter which was not in the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer engagements; then your ſpirit will be ſet at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117867:6"/> liberty, from the ſtrait wherein it is; which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds only from the want of this due conſideration, as I conceive; for when I put my ſelfe in your caſe (which to give you an unpartiall advice, I muſt do) I find but two wayes to bee ridd of the ſcruple <note n="1" place="margin">1. That the ſame main intent is to be in all publique engagements.</note> wherein you are inſnared; the one is by looking upon the main intent and fundamentall duty which is the life and ſoule of all theſe engagements. a thing unalterably one and the ſame in them all, <hi>viz: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſafety and welfare:</hi> to the proſecution of which (by the law of God in right reaſon) all publique en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements are at all times ſubordinate; though the meanes and wayes diverſly mentioned therein do varie.</p>
            <p>The other is by looking upon the evedent emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies <note n="2" place="margin">2. That the meanes are to be alterable by emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and the rules and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſtill the ſame.</note> which bring a change upon the meanes and wayes of proſecuting that intent, for it is undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that as the Circumſtances of Humane affaires alter, ſo the Engagements to proſecute Common ſafety and welfare therein are alterable. If then I can ſee that notwithſtanding the changeableneſſe of Emergencies, and the varietie of meanes reſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from thence, the ſame end is proſecuted by the ſame Rules and Principles, I am ſtill where I was; and no more out of my way, then if in a Voyage at Sea, whiles I am ſteering the ſame courſe; I have ſometimes faire, and ſometimes foule weather; or a winde ſometimes on this, ſometimes on that ſide of the Ship; which doth oblige the Marriners to nothing elſe but to trimme the Sails ſomewhat in another way, and ſtand more or leſſe carefully to their tackling.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117867:7"/>
            <p>Now to make ſome application of this to our <note place="margin">Particularly that we ſhould conſider.</note> caſe, I conceive whiles the King and Parliament did agree, and the truſt of Common ſafety was repoſed in him by his obſervance of the Lawes; The Oath of Allegiance like a faire gale in faire weather, did carry us on peaceably towards the Haven of common ſafety: but when he was judged to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage his Truſt unfaithfully, as intending not to ſteare his courſe by Law, but by will: the Covenant firſt like a ſide-wind on the one hand came in with foule weather, and then the Ingagement came in after it, as a change of winde on the other ſide of the Ship; both windes (as it is naturall to all ſide-windes) may ſerve to carry the Ship ſafely to her harbor, if the Marriners trimme the Sailes well, and the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers do not diſturb them in their functions: for if the ſame aim of common welfare is really intended by all three Ingagements, though they put it under different expreſſions; then you are not out of your way by taking any of them, if contrary to the rules of Chriſtianity, you muſt put out your ſelf out of it; For that which in the Oath of Allegiance is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be performed towards <hi>the juriſdictions an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed</hi> 
               <note n="1" place="margin">1. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all former engagements have one aime.</note> 
               <hi>unto the Imperiall Crown of this Realme,</hi> is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Nationall Covenant, <hi>the defence of the Kings Perſon and juſt Authority in the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the true Religion and liberties of the Kingdomes;</hi> all which in this preſent Ingagement is ſummed up and expreſſed <hi>by truth and faithfulneſs to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of England.</hi> The King, whiles he was in place of Truſt, was lookt upon as the Center of all common intereſts, and the Guardian of publique
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117867:7"/> ſafety; next unto the Lawes &amp; Legiſlative power, (for indeed he is no King, <hi>de jure,</hi> further then he agrees with theſe, and is a living Law in all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portments) but when he made himſelf Lawes, and would by power have ſet himſelf up inſtead of the <note n="2" place="margin">2. What the emergencie was which did alter our rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the King.</note> Law, the Truſtees of the Nation, to whom the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative and the Executive power doth primarily belong; thought it neceſſary to expreſſe the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Intereſts inſtruſted to his management, (and therefore by the Oath of Allegiance fixed upon his name) more directly, properly, and immediately, by the name of a Common-wealth, the ſafety of which was mainly intended by the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, although the words thereof mention our rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion onely to the King. If then when you took the Oath of Allegiance, your intention was not ſo much to oblige your ſelf to the welfare of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that way of ſettlement, Or to that way of ſettlement in order to Common welfare; as to the maintaining of a meere Royall greatneſſe for it ſelf, or to the maintaining of the Kings perſon in his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <note n="3" place="margin">3. What the miſtake was might bee at firſt in taking the oath of allegiance which now is to be rectified.</note> greatneſſe without reſpect to Common welfare; you did wholly miſtake the true and Legall intent of your Oath; and becauſe that ſuch an imagination had crept inſenſibly upon the ſpirits of many, by whom the King thought he could have exalted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be abſolute above the Nations liberties; therefore the Parliaments of both Nations finding that the name of a King was made an Idoll to the prejudice of that for which it was entertained, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Covenant, to rectifie that miſtake, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining that the true notion of Common welfare
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117867:8"/> and ſafety, did mainly and more neerely ſtand in the maietenance of Religion and Libertie, with the Rights and priviledges of Parliament, then in the having of a King; And ſince the Covenant hath been made void, as to the Nations, by reaſon of the hoſtilitie which hath been uſed between them; the Supreme power of this Nation, hath for it ſelf (as diſtinct from <hi>Scotland)</hi> determined in reference to the emergencies ſprung up ſince the making of the Covenant, that the true notion of Common welfare and ſafety, as to us, doth now ſtand in the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Common-wealth by it ſelf, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without a King and Houſe of Lords; For the having of a King and Houſe of Lords, were never by the rules of Chriſtianity and naturall equitie, underſtood otherwiſe to be uſefull, but in order to the Common-wealth: If therefore at any time, they wereby any taken up for themſelves, without a due ſubordination to the Common-wealth: It is a cleare miſtake of the true meaning of their conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; and by the principles of Naturall equitie, it is in the power of the Truſtees for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth to rectifie it, not is there any rule in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity which is not conſonant unto this, that <hi>Salvus populi</hi> is <hi>Suprema Lex,</hi> therefore they who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with Authority and power to ſee this Law kept: it according to the beſt of their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon different emergencies they alter the meanes of procuring it, and determine the way of proſecuting it; I cannot ſee what ſhould move the conſciences of particular men to be offended at <note n="4" place="margin">4. And what obligation lyes</note> them for ſo doing; or what warrant they can have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117867:8"/> in Chriſtianity or naturall equity to croſſe them in <note place="margin">upon private men to follow their rulers in the way of rectifying this miſtake.</note> their proceedings; If they preſcribe nothing to thoſe that are in ſubjection, which is in it ſelf impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or unlawfull; for if they doe preſcribe any ſuch thing, the Law of God is cleere; but if nothing of this kind be enjoyned, but onely that which is in its own nature alterable, according to circumſtances, (of which circumſtances they by their places are made Judges (and not I) then I ſuppoſe it is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably cleere, that my conſcience ought not to be bound up ſo to any one particular circumſtance of proceeding towards the publique ſafety, as that I may not have the liberty, upon the change of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, to follow them whom in alterable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters God hath made my Leaders for the publique good. For if it belongs to their proper charge to judge when, and where, and what change is to be made in the State; and how the publique good by Publique Reſolutions is to be advanced therein: and if I am bound to truſt them with this, and am not permitted by the law of God in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity or common equity to take upon me to be their judge, or to rule them, or to overrule the judgements of other men under them, againſt their ſenſe therein; then my conſcience is at libertie and under no guilt; Although I follow their dictates in affaires which are changeable: I muſt onely look to this, that in my private ſtation, my courſe upon all emergencies whatſoever be made anſwerable to the rules of Chriſtianity and equitie, in the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of mine own way whereof I am to bee a judge for my ſelf: and if in theſe circumſtances I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117867:9"/> ſubordinate by theſe rules my proceedings to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſafety, I diſcharge the dutie of a true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subject; and need not to trouble my ſpirit fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with higher matters: for if I doe trouble my ſelf with them, I bring my ſelf into a ſnare; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I obſerve not the bounds wherein I am at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. but goe beyond them.</p>
            <p>If theſe grounds cannot be contradicted Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally; then I ſuppoſe you will ſee thereby, that you <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the maine ſcruple</note> need not to be concluded ſo as you think you are obliged to be unalterably under the preciſe termes of the former Ingagements, in oppoſition to this; becauſe the true and Legall intent thereof is fully made out, ſo farre as concernes the ſhew of your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature in this laſt Ingagement.</p>
            <p>Therefore when you ſay in your diſcourſe to me, <hi>that the Oath of Allegiance and the Nationall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant are ſuch Sacred and everlaſting Obligements</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the maine ſcruple is propoſed.</note> 
               <hi>upon the conſciences of theſe that are under them, that they can never lawfully by enterring into any after-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements bind up themſelves from acting in good and lawfull wayes (if the Lord be pleaſed to open any ſuch in after times) for the aſsiſting of the juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions formerly annexed to the Imperiall Crown of this Realme; and for the preſerving of the Rights of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament then acknowledged, when the Covenant was taken, as farre forth as the Imperiall juriſdictions and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">And then opened and reſolved to ſhew.</note> 
               <hi>Parliamentary Rights are Conſiſtent with the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and liberties of the Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, when you aſſert this, you mean either to make every particular man a Judge of the reſtrictive clauſe how farre the Imperiall Jurisdictions and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117867:9"/> Parliamentary Rights, are conſiſtent with the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdome, or not; If you will make every particular man a competent judge of Imperiall juriſdictions, of Parliamentary Rights, and of the conſiſtency thereof in reference to all publique emergencies, with the true Religion and the Liberties of the Kingdome, you will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to ſhew me ſome grounds for this your opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and to make it appeare that I have erred in my fifth propoſition, which I ſuppoſe is not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted.</p>
            <p>But if you will not make every private or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular man a publique Judge of thoſe things; &amp; yet will allow them to be determined upon all emerge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t publique occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s by ſome body in a publique way; then it will I ſuppoſe fall to the ſhare of the Supreme powers for the time being to make this determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: &amp; if it be their right upon all emergencies to Judge what conſiſtencie there is between the true Religion &amp; the liberties of the Kingdome) which to me are eſſentiall requiſities of the common wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and ſafetie of a chriſtian common wealth with the imperiall Iuriſdictions and the Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Rights, then I ſuppoſe inferiours ought either to be concluded by their determination, or not. If not, how can it be ſuppoſed to be their right? what ground is there left upon ſuch occaſions, to avoid confuſion and to keepe a ſettlement of order and governments? But if they ought to be concluded by their ſuperiours in theſe things; and if their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Judge it fit or neceſſary for common ſafety, to alter the termes of theſe former publique engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117867:10"/> how can their obligements as to theſe things bee called everlaſting and never alterable? for if theſe that have a right to alter the ſame, find cauſe ſo <note place="margin">That all humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions being alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable no ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and unalterable obligement can be brought upon mens conſciences thereby</note> to do: and do as they find cauſe; and if none are to be Judges of the cauſes of that alteration but they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and if the reſt are to bee concluded by them, how can the obligement of the conſcience bee made everlaſting to a matter in it's owne nature alterable? I conceive then that no everlaſting obligement can bee brought upon the conſcience of any man but by God himſelfe in things by his authority made unalterable in their nature: and except that you can ſhew me that the Imperiall juriſdictions me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in the oath of Allegiance, and the Parliamentary pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and rights which then were, are made by his authority of a nature unalterable, I cannot allow you that by any engageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (though never ſo ſtrong) whereby wee are bound unto them, an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and unalterable obligement can be brought upon any mans conſcience: Our oaths never to alter; or to maintaine a forme of government in places and callings faithfully and truly, doth not make the forme neither in it's owne nature, nor as to us and to the publique unalterable by ſuperiour powers upon emergencies: they only bind us, nor to bee acceſſary as privat men, that is, by private pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices unto the alteration thereof, ſo long as they are conſiſtent with common ſafety, which is only deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable by the ſupreme power of a nation: for I ſuppoſe you never meant that thoſe obligements ſhould hold, although all publique welfare and common ſafety ſhould go to wrack for their ſakes.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117867:10"/> If then they were at the very time of their making to be underſtood, as ſubordinate unto this condition; that is, to be alterable if upon emergencies they ſhould be found contrary to common ſafety; how can they bee counted an evelaſting obligement as you would make them to bee? can your particular oath predetermine you in humane affaires not to be obliged to yeeld to divine Providence therein? or not to follow what is determined by the rules of Chriſtianity and equitie?</p>
            <p>You ſee then upon what grounds to my underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the preſent engagement and former oaths either agree; or are lawfully alterable without any juſt ſcruple of conſcience to bee made by me, in my place at the publique alteration thereof.</p>
            <p>This is your main doubt; and thus to me it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</p>
            <p>The other doubts which (you ſay your ſelfe) lie not neer the heart of the buſineſſe; I need not meddle withall: for if theſe principles which I have laid; and the application thereof which I have made, bee without exception, then other by-matters cannot reach to the conſcience in this buſineſſe: yet <note place="margin">Concerning ſome ſecondary doubts.</note> 
               <hi>ex abundanti;</hi> that I may pay you ſome intereſt for the long delay of diſcharging this debt: and that nothing may be wanting which may tend to clear your thoughts in this diſquirie; I ſhall take the other doubts of your diſcourſe as you have offered them into conſideration, Firſt you ſay that my aſſertion concerning the power of Subordinate officers is, Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable. My aſſertion was; that Subordinate officers belonging to a State are bound to Judge of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117867:11"/> the rights of <hi>theſe that are over them; both by which</hi> 
               <note n="1" place="margin">1. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the right which ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate officers have to Judg of the actings of ſuperiours.</note> 
               <hi>they ſtand in their places of ſupremary; and by which they proceede in their actings towards Subjects, leſt they bee made the inſtruments of arbitrary power and Tyrannie.</hi> This aſſertion you ſay is Queſtionable. But to cleer the doubt which you may have of it, take notice, that I ſpeake of officers belonging to a State, as immediately ſubordinate thereunto, and not depending upon a King, though the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Officer therein: I ſuppoſe then that they are appointed by the Authority of the State it ſelf, and placed in their Offices thereby, &amp; not by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the K. This being preſuppoſed, that theſe officers are thus created &amp; ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in their places, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that which I have ſaid of them to bee a truth very matteriall to be cleared, to ſhew not onely how a people may lawfully (I meane by the law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) free themſelves from the danger of Tyranny; but how private men who are in no publique place of Truſt; may be induced to diſcern what is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible for publique Safety by the Authority of their Leaders. To have then this matter determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; we may reflect upon two things: Firſt, what <note place="margin">To determine that which is doubtfull concerning this matter is conſidered.</note> Conſtitutions and Cuſtomes the Nations pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Freedome have made, or keep up, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſubordination of Officers, under their high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Powers, Secondly, what the Ground and main Principle of ſubordination of Officers is in Nature, and what the end of their imployment under Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Powers is. <note place="margin">What ſorts of officers are in uſe among free nations</note>
            </p>
            <p>We find by the Conſtitutions or Cuſtomes of free Nations, three ſorts of ſubordinate Officers in their States; Some are placed by the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117867:11"/> of a Nation in their Offices; Some by him that is in the place of Supremacy over it: ſome by both joyntly.</p>
            <p>The firſt, although in reſpect of Power they are leſſe, and in Order they are after him who is Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme (becauſe his place is firſt, and his Power is of a larger extent then theirs) yet becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not their places from him, but from the ſame <note n="1" place="margin">1. Such as are ſet up by the State it ſelf.</note> Authority whence he hath his; Therefore they are not accountable to him of their proceedings, but unto thoſe onely who gave them their authority.</p>
            <p>Thus in <hi>Poland, Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Denmarke,</hi> by the ancient conſtitution of thoſe States, there are ſeverall offices of ſtate, as chancellors and chief Iuſtices, and Admirals who are appointed by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; and ſo hold their places from it, and not from their Kings. Thus you had in England a Conſtable of the Kingdome, whom the Parliament did appoint. But King James never reſted till he was removed. Thus in the Empire the electors are under the Emperour; not as his officers, but as Officers of the Empire it ſelfe; they are inſtruſted to be Judges of the right and title of him who is to bee Supreme; and they have a power in their colledge to controul him in his proceedings if he become exorbitant; for they may ſay to him, what doſt thou? this then is an allay of his emperiall power; and ſo are all officers of this nature any where elſe; an allay to the abſoluteneſſe of the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of ſubordinate officers, are ſuch as depend meerly upon him that is ſupreme in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117867:12"/> for he hath power in the charge wherewith he <note n="2" place="margin">2. Such as are ſet up by the Supreme Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of State.</note> is intruſted to make and unmake his owne inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo that they are to bee counted properly his officers ſubordinate to the charge, whereof he is the chiefe adminiſtrator: theſe are therefore reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponſable unto him firſt, and then alſo to the State, even as he himſelfe is by whom they are employed. Theſe officers although they have no paaticular truſt repoſedin the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; yet becauſe they are made inſtrumentall in the adminiſtration of a truſt which the nation hath repoſed in him, who doth create them &amp; ſet them at work, therefore they are reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable for the effects of their adminiſtration, to thoſe from whom the firſt truſt doth proceed; and to whoſe advantage or diſadvantage the way of their adminiſtration doth finally redound: whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes that theſe officers are bound both for their own ſafety, &amp; for the obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which lieth upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them towards the ſtate, to judge both of the power which their ſuperiour takes upon himſelfe to exerciſe, and whereof he pretends to have a right to have them his inſtruments, and alſo of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and property of the worke which they are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in, leſt they ſhould under him at his will, being led blindfold to obey, become inſtruments of Tyrannie and injuſtice, Thus the ſervants of Saul (though ſouldiers who are otherwiſe bound to a moſt ſtrict obedience juſtly refuſed to bee the executioners, of his crueltie in killing the prieſts of the Lord. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 17.</p>
            <p>The third ſort of ſubordinate officers, are ſuch as are conſtituted by the joint conſent &amp; concurrence of both; as when the Repreſentations of a free
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117867:12"/> State; <hi>viz:</hi> the ſupream councell thereof, agree with a governour whom they call and chuſe; that he ſhall place none in ſpeciall offices under him; <note place="margin">The third by ſuch as are ſet up by both Iointly.</note> for the adminiſtration of their publique concerments but ſuch as ſhall be taken out of a certaine number whom they ſhall preſent unto him: ſo that the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of two or three Perſons, indefinitely, as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the place, is in the power of the Senate; but the diſtinct appointment and nomination of one who is to have the place, is left to the Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. Thus in the Low Countries Burgemaſters of Towns &amp; Sheriffs of the Territories were conſtituted by the Prince who was their Governour; &amp; in ſeverall Provnces, there &amp; elſewhere, other Officers of State, are conſtituted by ſuch a concurrence of Election on the one, and Nomination on the other ſide, that the power of conferring authority is divided; and the ſubordinate officers receive in their places a truſt from both, and become accountable unto both in ſeverall reſpects.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Cuſtomes and Conſtitutions of <note n="2" place="margin">2. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple &amp; ground of ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</note> free Nations, to prevent the abuſe of Power in their Officers.</p>
            <p>As for the Principle whence naturally Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination doth proceed; I conceive it to be the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Unity and Order in a ſocietie, for the manageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of publique affaires, wherein all are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, for to avoid the diſſolving of Societies, joint Relations and Duties belonging thereunto, muſt be ſetled as a common intereſt, and to avoid the confuſion which would follow upon the manageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of that intereſt, if it were left to every one to doe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117867:13"/> in it, what he ſhould thinke good; the Truſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of muſt needs lie in ſome hands; and the nature of that Truſt muſt be determined by a law, which ſhould be the effect of the free conſent of thoſe that are inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted in the Publique to provide the welfare thereof, and becauſe no ſingle hand can be every where by it ſelfe; at the ſame time; to diſcharge a large Truſt which hath many parts; whereof the one is to bee made helpfull to the other: therefore many are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in order to one another, and all to the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of power by whom they are ſet aworke.</p>
            <p>And concerning the direct &amp; Immediate end of ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, <note n="3" place="margin">3. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the end of ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</note> it is to bring all tranſactions to one iſſue; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely to the ſafety &amp; welfare of the Communalitie, by the a dminiſtration of duties according to lawes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by every one is to have his due from another; which is called Juſtice. And the Indirect and Accidentall end of Subordination &amp; coordination of Officers under a Supream, is to prevent by the bounds of offices, and the diſtribution of Power belonging thereunto; the Tyrannicall incroachment of Power into one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle hand; leſt an abſolute Arbitrary dominion be taken up over thoſe, who by the law of Nature and of Chriſtianity being free, put themſelves voluntarily in an orderly Subjection to a Superiour power. For in my apprehenſion all humane actions, whether na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall or ſpirituall depend upon power: (I meane by power a might and ſtrength to produce an effect) and whereſoever God or men have diſpoſed of power, and placed ſtrength to act for a publique intereſt; there <note place="margin">What is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly meant by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> is alſo a right to adminiſter that power to that effect; that is to put it forth towards others to that end: This
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117867:13"/> right I do call Authority; becauſe it intitles a man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameablely to become the Author of the undertakings, for which he hath received power; and to bee a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of others who ſhould concurre therein with him: this right or authority is not unlimited or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurable only to the utmoſt extent of what power is able to do; ſo that he who hath power may do with it what ever he will and can; but it is bounded in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the end for which it is given; and in ſocieties of reaſonable men by a law to become ſerviceable to a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good: and if upon emergencies no poſitive law bee extant to determine the Circumſtantiall way of uſing power and authority; then the generall law of Nature and of Chriſtianity is to take place, which is the law of liberty, by which all caſes may bee determined ſo farre as to make our actions at leaſt without offence, if not alſo acceptable to thoſe to whom they are done. This law is, give no occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the fleſh, but by love ſerve one another; and <hi>the rule of this ſervice is; what ever you would have others</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 13. Luke 6. 31.</note> 
               <hi>do to you; do ye to them likewiſe.</hi> To be in authority is to have a right to act in a place for the publique good, ſo as to bee an author of ſome undertaking; and to be obliged to lead others therein: which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation doth naturally ariſe from the truſt of power put in the hands of him that hath received it, to act towards thoſe and for thoſe that give it; to the end for which it is beſtowed: whereof there is a cleer example in the power given to the conſtable of every pariſh; who is obliged to be the author of publique undertakings in the ſphere of the Truſt repoſed in him, though otherwiſe he is a man of no reſpect.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117867:14"/>
            <p>Upon theſe grounds the ſubordinate Offices of a State, may judge and act in their places for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, to prevent Tyranny, and the incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of abſolute power in him who is intruſted with the higheſt power: and if theſe grounds be ſound (as I ſuppoſe they are) they will cleare the juſtice and equitie of the Parliament proceedings in their late Tranſactions with the King; whereupon a change of Government is fallen out in this State; which being brought about by the Supremacy of power in the Repreſentatives of the people, and by a right to act for the publique good in the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Officers of the State; private Perſons are bound to acquieſce thereat, and to regulate their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions according to the Rules and Principles of Naturall equitie and Chriſtianity in their ſeverall places, as Emergencies doe require.</p>
            <p>This matter which you did call Queſtionable, but would not debate, I have thus endeavoured to open ſomewhat largely, becauſe it is of uſe to undeceive us from the falſe Notion of Royall power, which doth inſenſibly breed many ſcruples; when it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up unawares, without a due examination of the right which it hath to Supremacie, in a Nation which is to be governed by Lawes, and not by will of a Monarch But you have other matters in your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which you thought more worthy of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; and you take them chiefly from three Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of my conſiderations; to ſhew that they are not ſatisfactory to reſolve your preſent Scruple; to theſe I ſhall alſo impart unto you my preſent thoughts.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117867:14"/>
            <p>In Pag. 6. I ſay, that private men cannot be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note n="2" place="margin">2. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the guilt of breach of covenant in private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> guilty of a breach of Covenant, becauſe there was a change of Government brought upon the State by others in a way to them unreſiſtable in their places.</p>
            <p>To this you anſwer: <hi>As I was not guilty (ſay you) of what others did (whether well or ill, I leave it free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the judgement of the Lord and their own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) in a way unreſiſtable as to me in my place; ſo I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lawfully bind up my ſelf from acting in my place in lawfull wayes for the accompliſhment of my Oath and Covenant, without guilt of ſinne, and deſpiſing the Oath of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer: That the preſent Engagement, if you look upon it as containing a perpetuall Duty to be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth; is <note place="margin">That the engagement brings no ſuch guilt upon any</note> ſo farre from binding you up from acting that which in your place, is fitting for you to doe, towards the accompliſhment of your Oath and Covenant (ſo farre as they are binding) that it rather doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige you to act in your preſent place, that which is the ground, by which your Oath and Covenant did Legally bind you to a Duty; and without which they could not at all be binding, which in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Diſcourſe and elſewhere alſo I have ſhewed.</p>
            <p>As for me, I doe not think it lawfull to ſuffer my ſelf to bee bound up, by any Emergencies what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, or any Reſolutions of mine own, from the Intentions of performing known Duties; Nor doe I think it lawfull for any Chriſtian to think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117867:15"/> tied by any Oaths or Covenants whatſoever, ſo, as at any time he ſhould be thereby bound up from the performance of any cleere and undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Duty towards God and Men in his place; therefore I plainly aſſert that the Allegation of Oathes and Covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, which doth tend to take me off from an undoubted Duty, is undoubredly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifull: for which cauſe, when the Engagement was offered unto me, I did ſet my ſelf to look upon it, not as you doe, to ſee what ſenſe it might beare contrary to any former Duty; but to ſee what the Duty was which it did directly require, and which I was bound at this time, <hi>Rebus ſic Stantibus,</hi> or at all times to intend: and having made a Declaration of my Senſe in taking the Engagement to this effect; and my Senſe being accepted, or not accepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by thoſe that were impoſers thereof; I thought it my Duty to reſt there, and not to trouble my ſelf any further; either with the Conjectures of future Contingencies, as ſome doe: or as others <note place="margin">But that the prejudices which ſome entertain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of our change layeth the imputation of that guilt.</note> doe, with jealouſies over the intentions of my Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; or with the Cenſures of miſcarriages, which others imagine to be in thoſe over whom they are ſet to be Judges; for although you leave it (as you ſay) freely to God to judge, whether the preſent Change be well or ill brought about; yet give me leave to tell you, that I cannot perceive that your Spirit is free without prejudice againſt them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the change: for if you had no prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thoughts that way; you could not make ſuch a conſtruction of the engagement as you do, relating to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117867:15"/> the change as it is oppoſite to a duty which you think lyes upon you by the tye of an Oath and Covenant. Therefore if there bee a clear and perpetuall duty both in the former and latter Engagements in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wherein their ſenſes agree, and yet if you will not own that, but take up that rather where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thier ſenſes may ſeeme to diſagree; I may conclude that you either miſtake the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the oath and Covenant; or that you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not your tye at this time, in obſerving the ſame, how farre it is to bee extended: for if it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee extended, to oblige you to neglect any preſent and ſeaſonable Duty; then you miſapply your ſenſe thereof, to the preſent occaſions, ſo, as to make it a ſnare unto your conſcience; which for your owne Peace ſake you ſhould endeavour to avoid.</p>
            <p>But to that which I ſay in pag. 8. concerning <note n="3" place="margin">3. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the tye of former engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ememts that it is extinct.</note> the tye of the former Oathes that is extinct ſo farre as the things promiſed therein are become either impoſſible in themſelves; or in reference to our calling unlawfull to bee proſecuted: you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that <hi>you cannot</hi> apprehend your obligation to bee extinct towards the matter of <hi>the oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance and covenant, whiles you may poſſibly in lawfull wayes conſiſtent with the publique welfare and liberties of the Common Wealth and agreable to your calling (viz. by Petitioning, humble Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance to the Parliament, or the like Peaceable courſe) have an opportunity offered you to endeavour the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and preſervation of the ancient rights and</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:117867:16"/> 
               <hi>Privilegdes of Parliament and the Kings Authority, in the preſervation of the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then to that which I ſay pag. 9. that it is not lawfull for any in a private calling to attend the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of that which by publique Authority hath been aboliſhed; you adde further by the way of anſwer that is true in a way of force and fraud; but that it holds not <hi>as to wayes humble, peaceable, and conſiſtent with publique welfare; to which the Oath and Covenant, immediately and undiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly extend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which I ſhall anſwer: that humane lawes <note place="margin">Becauſe humane lawes relare only to outward actions, and not to ſecret ententions.</note> ſuch as the Engagement is, reſpect only mens out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward actions, and oblige us to bee true and faithfull therein to what wee declare, but the inward pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of the mind which occaſionally may bee fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, no lawes of man can regulate: theſe are ſubject only to the generall rules of equitie which Gods law doth preſcribe; therefore if emergencies bee ſo circumſtantiated as you ſuppoſe they may be, to incline your thoughts to ſuch a purpoſe as you ſpeake of, the rules of naturall equitie and Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie muſt direct you then as then, in declaring your deſires how to make them harmeleſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the publique welfare: and what need you feare that any will harme you if you follow that <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 13.</note> which is good? but that you ſhould imagine ſtill that your obligation to maintaine Royaltie, is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct, is ſomewhat a wonder unto me: for if the matter of the Oath of Allegiance and Covenant had
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117867:16"/> any legall being, you might and ought to intend the preſerva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion thereof in your place and calling; but ſince that doth clearly ceaſe to have a being, it is not imaginable to me that any private man in his Sphere ſhould be bound to in end or endeavour the reſtitution thereof. For that the forme of a <note place="margin">Becauſe the matter of the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance doth clearely ceaſe.</note> Royall government hath no reall being amongſt us to oblige us to maintaine it; is ſo cleare that none can make any doubt of it; and that the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te Kings progeny (though they have a being innature, yet) have no legall being in place of truſt or government as to us; is no leſſe evident; therefore what ſhould be the ground to make you believe; that your former obligement to Royaltie, or to the late Kings heirs (who did forfeit his place of Truſt, as for himſelfe ſo for his poſteritie) ſhould ſtill bee binding, is a kind of riddle unto me, upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count you take up that obligation to continue: for if the Allegiance which you promiſed to the King, to his heirs and ſucceſſors could oblige you, no more but to be a good Subject in your place, and to maintaine him and them in their Legall ſtanding over you, by your legall ſubmiſſion unto him and them; then it followeth, that in caſe either they ſhould have no ſuch ſtanding over you, or you ſhould remove under them; that your obligation comes to an end: for either way the relation ceaſing the obligation is made void. Nor is there any clauſe to oblige you to reſtore them to ſuch a ſtate, in caſe they ſhould come to faile of it; nor could any ſuch clauſe bee obligatorie although you you had promiſed it, becauſe no man can lawfully
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117867:17"/> bee obliged to that which is not in his power. to effect.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ſay, that by vertue of theſe former <note place="margin">Becauſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments bind not to a reſtitution of Royaltie if aboliſhed by publique Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</note> Engagements, it can be no part of your Duty to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the reſtitution of thoſe things, which are now by publique Authority aboliſhed; For if this ſhould be an abſolute Duty, then alſo it muſt be a Duty to proſecute the ſame abſolutely; and if I am bound abſolutely, (that is without any condition) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the reſtitution of a Royall Power over me; Then I cannot with a good Conſcience acquieſce at the abolition thereof upon any termes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: nay, although the abolition be never ſo well and lawfully brought about: which to aſſert is a great Paradox, and yet except all this be granted, your poſition cannot ſtand. Therefore I am cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced, not onely by the Law of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding me to be ſubject to the Powers that are over me; but by the true and Legall intent of the former Engagements, that it is my Duty at this time to acquieſce at the abolition of things pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely removed: and if ſo, then it cannot be my Duty to proſecute the Reſtitution thereof; and if it is not my Duty now to proſecute their Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then alſo it is not lawfull for me to intend ſuch a thing: for if I intend it, I am reſolved in my heart to attempt that which is no part of my preſent Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to worke a change upon the preſent ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which the Word of God forbids me to meddle withall, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 21. For as formerly I might not in my Sphere intend to bring a change upon the State from the ſettlement that then was;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117867:17"/> ſo now the ſame Rule holds, I may not intend to bring a change upon the State from the ſettlement that now is. And although I take this to be a Rule for me in my private place to order my purpoſes by; yet I doe not thinke this Rule binds the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power of a Nation; the Repreſentatives thereof, when they are in a body acting their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Truſt; as if then it were not lawfull for them <note place="margin">Becauſe the repreſentatives of a nation may be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ergencies to alter the forme of Royall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> according to Emergencies to bee obliged to alter the formes of Goverment in the Nation: for although every one of them in their private ſtation and at their admiſſion to their Truſt, may have taken the Oath and promiſed to maintaine the Government in that forme wherein they found it when they tooke their oath, yet when they are upon the delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the publique; wherein <hi>Salus Populi</hi> is to be their <hi>Suprema Lex.</hi> No humane conſtitution or particular obligation, can bind them in a body from what they ſhall find moſt expedient in that caſe to bee done. And if the emergencies may be ſuch, as to oblige them in the diſcharge of their truſt to alter the goverme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for publique ſafeties, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their oath of Allegiance to maintaine it: far more when the alteration is wrought publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may private men (who have no power to judge of ſuch concerments; nor to act therein without their leader bee diſpenſed withall, from being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to intend the reſtauration of that which by publique authority hath been aboliſhed, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Oath, binding them to maintaine it whiles it was in being.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe yougive me cauſe here to reflect upon that which was formerly alledged in your words,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117867:18"/> concerning the Oath of Allegiance and Nationall Covenant, that you count them ſuch ſacred and everlaſting obligements that nothing can abſolve <note place="margin">Becauſe the property of an everlaſting obligement cannot bee fixed upon meer humane engagements.</note> men from acting towards the accompliſhment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: therefore I think it expedient to ſuggeſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing further unto your conſideration, for which I think thoſe Oaths not to bee ſuch everlaſting obligements as you apprehend them to bee; which is this. That nothing can be an everlaſting ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligement upon the conſcience to bind it unto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall purpoſe of proſecuting the ſame, but that which is in it's owne nature a perpetuall Duty, and that only is to me a perpetuall duty, whereof the rule and the direct object is to men unalterable.</p>
            <p>But to aſſert the Juriſdictions formerly annexed to the Imperiall Crown of this Realme, &amp;c. is not in its own nature a perpetuall Duty, in reſpect the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of that Action is not as to men unal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erable: therefore it cannot be an everlaſting Obligement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Conſciences, to bind them unto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall purpoſe of proſecuting the ſame. Now that to ſupport <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or to endeavour any other Earthly thing, relating to State affaires, is not in it's own nature a perpetuall Duty; I ſuppoſe is to your ſelf ſo cleare, that I ſhall not need to prove it; for no man can be ignorant that all Earthly <hi>matters</hi> and Relations are wholly alterable according to the Emergencies and circumſtances: whence followeth immediately that the Conſcience cannot be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly bound to intend the proſecution thereof; but onely conditionally, according to the main end for which ſuch Obligements are allowed to be taken, and according to the Rule by which they are to be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117867:18"/> proſecuted, which in private men is not without the conduct of their Leaders, who are inſtructed with the Supreme management of publique affaires; if then the Leaders, as heretofore they ſaw cauſe to aboliſh <hi>Monarchy,</hi> ſhould ſee cauſe hereafter to ſet it up again, and thereupon ſhould intend a new change in the <hi>State;</hi> I think it would in this Caſe be lawfull for you to concurre with them therein: whence we muſt conclude, that as the Rulers of this <hi>State</hi> by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Engagement, cannot intend to oblige them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, never to intend upon what Emergencies ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to alter the preſent Eſtabliſhment; ſo the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects thereof by taking the ſame Engagement, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuppoſed to bind up themſelves from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Leaders in the reſolutions which in that kind they may take; for if upon new E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergencies the Supreme Powers ſhould lead the people to intend a new Change with them; without all doubt they may lawfully doe it; but except you ſuppoſe the conduct and guiding of theſe; I ſee not how it can be lawfull in the aime of any private man to precure it by any meanes whatſoever: becauſe by ſo doing private men without their Leaders go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their Line. Therefore ſtill I conclude that private men may not attempt the reſtoring of that which by publique Authority hath been aboliſhed, otherwiſe then under the conduct of their Superiour Powers.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt thing which you queſtion, is that which I ſay pag. 9. <hi>That if in order to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, I were bound by Oath to proſecute a buſineſſe, and ſhould find that by my proſecution of it, the publique would rather be hindred then advanced; that in ſuch</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:117867:19"/> 
               <hi>a caſe my Oath would oblige me rather to deſiſt from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting</hi> 
               <note n="4" place="margin">4. Concerning releaſement from oaths upon a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ition.</note> 
               <hi>the buſineſſe, then to proceed therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which you ſay thus; <hi>That this being Dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically delivered, doth ſeeme altogether unſound;</hi> which you endeavour to ſhew by the Example of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> who is condemned for breaking his Oath upon ſuch a pretence to the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi> for you ſay; <hi>No queſtion Zedekiah became ſubject, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">And Zedeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah his Caſe &amp; plea for the breaking of his Oath.</note> 
               <hi>was bound by Oath to the King of Babylon in Order to the common good of his Kingdome, and afterward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending (as we may be confident) that it would be more uſefull for the publique good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, to ſtand free from the Babylonian Yoke; by the aſſiſtance of the King of Egypt, he attempted the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of that freedome, contrary to his Oath; and became guilty of Oath and Covenant breaking before God; for which he is deeply charged and threa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> by the Lord, Ezech.</hi> 17. So then your Argument from hence is this; If <hi>Zedekiah</hi> did behave himſelf in breaking his Oath according to the Rule which you lay down; and yet was condemned by the Lord for ſo doing; Then the Rule which you own is not ſound: But <hi>Zedekiah</hi> did ſo, <hi>Ergo,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To anſwer this doubt; I ſhall confeſſe, that if <hi>Zedekiah</hi> his Caſe was the ſame with that which I ſuppoſe; and if he followed the Rule which I give <note place="margin">The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment raiſed upon Zedeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs caſe.</note> in that Caſe; and yet is condemned by the Lord for following that Rule, then my Rule is not ſound; but I conceive you will find (if you look ſomewhat neerer to the buſineſſe) that his Caſe is not the ſame with that which I ſuppoſe; nor that he followed the rule which I gave in this Caſe, nor that he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Lord for following that Rule.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:117867:19"/>
            <p>The caſe which I ſuppoſe is concerning a particular <note place="margin">By ſhewing the difference of the caſe in hand with that of Zedekiah.</note> buſineſſe which I am bound by Oath to proſecute as a private man in order to the publique good: whereof I am ſuppoſed to be a competent Judge ſo farre as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to that particular buſineſſe: I ſay, if my Oath binds me to proſecute it in order to the publique good; and I upon circumſtances can judge that the proſecution will not advance but oppoſe the publique good, then my Oath binds me not to proceed, but to deſiſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the expreſſe condition of the Oath which is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly binding to the proſecution, is deſect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve. But in <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah</hi> l. is caſe this cannot be ſuppoſed: For firſt, his Oath was not concerning my particular buſineſſe, but a generall ſubmiſſion to be a faithfull Subject to the King of <hi>Babylon:</hi> nor was he a private man managing his own buſineſſe, but he was the Subſtitute or Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> over the publique <hi>State</hi> of the Kingdome of <hi>Iudah:</hi> nor was it left to him to be the ſole competent Judge of the <hi>matter,</hi> whether his ſubmiſſion to the Crown of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould tend to the publique goodyea or no; for that was already abſolutely determined; and he was ſworne to be ſubject without any other condition; but that he ſhould be King to that effect. The caſe then as it is by me propoſed, is not applyable to <hi>Zedekiah:</hi> Therefore it comes not to be conſidered by my Rule, nor had he the liberty left him to make uſe of my Rule, for my rule ſpeakes of a conditionall Oath; and no ſuch thing can be ſuppoſed in this caſe. My rule ſuppoſes me to be free to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute or leave my buſineſſe according to mine own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as I ſhall ſee it ſubordinate to a publipue good; but the buſineſſe to which he was ſworne, was not left to him to judge otherwiſe of, then was already determined by his ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord the King of Babylon, <hi>viz.</hi> that his ſubjection to him ſhould be the ſafety of the Nation; his Rebellion from him, ſhould be his and their deſtruction: nor was the caſe when Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117867:20"/> rebelled, altered from what it was at firſt when he ſwore ſubjection; which I ſuppoſe in my rule muſt fall out ſeeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Zedekiah could not make uſe of my rule in his caſe; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that he could not be condemned for making uſe of it.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this matter is worth a further diſquirie; and <note place="margin">And how our obligation to bee ſubject to the King by the Oath of Allegiance and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, differ from Zedeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs oath to the King of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</note> I ſee that the caſe which I have propoſed undefinitely, may bee applyed to the oath of Allegiance under which we ſtood for the publique good; and to the Nationall covenant; concerning which you may ſay perhaps of us as I have ſaid of Zedekiah, that they bind us abſolutely to bee ſubjects to the King, and leave it not to us to judge whether our ſubjection to him ſhould tend to the publique good yea or no: therefore to reſolve this doubt alſo, I ſhall compare our condition of ſubjection, and our Oath binding him thereunto towards the King of Babylon, and then if the caſe bee found alike; I ſhall confeſſe that we are now, as much bound, to the maſter of our Oath as he then was bound to the maſter of his: but if his relation to the King of Babylon was wholly different from ours to our King; if his Oath of ſubmiſſion to that King was of another kind then ours was to our King, and if his way of freeing himſelf from his relation and from the bond of his Oath towards the King of Babylon was quite another thing then what hath been intended by us; then I hope you will not make our caſe parallel to his; but in all theſe matters a vaſt difference, will be found between him and us, ergoe his guilt cannot be made ours.</p>
            <p>Firſt his Relation to the King of Babylon, was to be the vaſſall <note place="margin">In reſpect of the relation wherein he ſtood to Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezer and wee to the King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> of a Conquerour for the K. of B. having ruined the ſtate of Iudah and ſubdued the Nation, made Zedekiah his vaſſall to rule it in his name, who bound himſelfe by Oath ſo to do: but wee ſtood not under our K. as a Conquered natio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by him, but as free borne ſubiects under a King bound to rule by law.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Oath by which <hi>Zedekiah</hi> did ſubmit himſelf to the K. of <hi>Babylon,</hi> was preſcribed according to <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> will, and no doubt it was abſolutely to keep the Nation in his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection <note place="margin">In reſpect of the oath which he tooke, and wee tooke.</note> without any condition of Laws, of Priviledges, of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or of any ſuch thing ſuppoſed or impoſed on <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> part; but the Oath by which the people of this Nation were bound to be ſubjects to their K. was by thoſe that fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and impoſed it, made to be taken and kept under certain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: <hi>viz.</hi> that we ſhould be Subjects by Law and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and that our ſubjection to him ſhould be conſiſtent with the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117867:20"/> priviledges of Par. &amp; the native liberties of the nation, &amp; no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: and to make this Oath binding, thoſe who impoſed it upon the people, had power to impoſe another Oath which was recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call thereunto upon the King, that he might be bound to them to rule by law, as well as they to him to be obedient according to law: by which meanes the tye of the Oath was ſeverall wayes limited, and the K. himſelf as well bound up in his commands, as they in their obedience by a Law: but no ſuch thing can be imagined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, his way of freeing himſelf from his relation and oath, was <note place="margin">In reſpect of his way of breaking of his oath and of our way of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freed from it.</note> by a direct rebellion contrary to the intent of his Oath and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; but our way of freeing ourſelves hath been Legall, agreeable to the Tenor of the Law and to the ſenſe of the Authority by which the Oath was given and made Legall: for the Oath in the ſenſe of the Legiſlative power was never abſolute, but conditionall; it did not binde us to the Kings perſonall and arbitrary will and command, but to his government and authority as he had a leg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſtanding: and the ſenſe of the Parl. touching the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, how farre we are thereby intended to be made ſubordinate to the K. is expreſſed in the Nationall Covenant which makes it clearly conditionall: and the Parl. it ſelf hath freed us long agoe from the obligation of that condition, by declaring that he had forfeited his right to govern any longer. So that the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and us, is ſo vaſt in this point of being free from the Oath, that I can find no reſemblance at all in the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for as in our caſe if the K. kept not his Oath to his Subjects, they were abſolved <hi>De lure</hi> from their Oath to him, in <hi>Zedekiah</hi> his Caſe there was no ſuch contract between the K. of <hi>Babylon</hi> and him, but the will of the Conquerour was his law; in our caſe there was a Law to Regulate both the K. and us in keeping of our Oathes; and Truſtees in Parl. to ſee that law kept; who herein were above the King, and in caſes of aberration empowered, to ſee faults amended, both in King and Subjects; but in the caſe of <hi>Zedekiah</hi> there is no ſuch thing; the Authority of <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> was above all Humane poſitive Lawes, and <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was ſworn to be abſolutely his Subject in ſuch things, and to keep his people in ſubjection thereunto; In our Caſe, the King to whom we were ſworne, deſerted his Station of Government, and left his truſt by leaving his Parliament, and levying warre againſt it; but in <hi>Zedekiah</hi> his Caſe, no ſuch thing is imaginable; In our caſe the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117867:21"/> Parliament having the Supreme Authority of the Nation, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conquered the King, doth oblige us to be true and faithfull to the free States without him; but in Zedekiah his Caſe no ſuch thing is conceiveable: and many other things of a different nature might be inſiſted upon in our Caſe, which cannot be brought home to Zedekiah his Caſe, to free him from his Oath, as we are freed from ours: for his whole action was directly oppoſite to the cleare intent of his Oath; and to all the circumſtances of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good of the Nation oft he <hi>Iews,</hi> as the Lord himſelf doth intimate in <hi>Ezech.</hi> Ch. 17. &amp; 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. but our actions in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Parliament, have been all along conſonant to the Legall intentof our Oath, by which we are abſolved from our relation to the King, as alſo by all the circumſtances of his miſcarriages, of his illegall proceedings, and of his breach of truſt towards the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like: by all the circumſtances of the publike good to be procured without him; not according to the iudgement of particular men (for in this Caſe my Rule, is not to make every private man a Iudge of the publique good) but of the Supreme Authority of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and by all the circumſtances of his removall from the Throne, and of our preſent ſtanding under the Supreme power of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which now is over us. So that to Oblige the conſcience of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men to intend the reſtauration of a royall governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t upon the account of ſuch an Oath, from which we are made ſo many wayes Legally free; is to me a great miſtake of Duty, and a dangerous ſnare to intangle weake ſpirits into the occaſions of publique di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances; whereunto I know you are not inclined to give any the leaſt Overtures: but the danger is that other men who are of a turbulent diſpoſition, and by ſuch a miſtake of their diſſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and ſeeming Obligation to that which is contrary to their preſent Duty, being otherwiſe perſonally diſcontented, may ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and heighten their diſtempers to a full reſolution of publique diſturbance, and endeavours of diſtructive unſettlements; from which I am ſure your genius and pious thoughts do abhorre.</p>
            <p>Thus you have that which I can at preſent ſuggeſt, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Lord ſo to addreſſe, as it may tend moſt to your comfort, if you be ſtill unſatisfied; and if you be already ſatisfied, that it may be a meanes to confirme you in that which is agreeable to his holy Will, and profitable to the good of the Common-wealth of Iſrael, in the love of which, I ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Weſt minſter</hi> 
                  <date> this 8. <hi>Decem.</hi> 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your faithfull and affectionate Servant, <hi>I. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
